בוקר טוב *Boker tov*. Today's דף daf *daf* is צ"ו *Tzadik Vav*.
We pick up on the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* right after the משנה
Mishna, *Mishna* on י"ד עמוד ב׳ *Yud Dalet amud bet*. The משנה
Mishna. *Mishna* mentioned a couple of things that you had thirteen of,
thirteen שופרות *shofars*, that's what we're going to focus on. But then
also a fascinating story about when it mentions thirteen bowing downs that
they did in the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash *Beit HaMikdash* that the
house of רבן גמליאל *Rabban Gamliel* and of רבי חנניה סגן הכהנים
*Rabbi Hananya Sgan HaKohanim* would add a fourteenth time opposite דיר העצים
Deir Ha'etzim, *Deir HaEtzim*, the room where they kept the wood. And
they had a tradition that the ארון Aron *Aron* was buried underneath
that room and the story where somebody כהן Kohen, *Kohen* actually saw
something unusual about the flooring in one section and wanted to tell
somebody about it and dropped dead. And that was a proof that
he had obviously discovered the secret hiding place of the ארון Aron,
*Aron*. So let's take a look at the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*.
I'm sorry, it's צ"ו עמוד ב׳ *Tzadik Vav amud bet*. I keep
on making... we're צ"ז *Tzadik Zayin* is the official דף daf *daf*,
we pick up on צ"ו עמוד ב׳ *Tzadik Vav amud bet*. I
don't know what I said.
The ארון Aron, *Aron* from the בית bayit? ראשון *Bayit Rishon*. The
ארון Aron *Aron* from...
we're about to find out about that. But they didn't have it
in the בית bayit, שני *Bayit Sheni*. So the question is what
happened to it? And according to this משנה Mishnah *Mishna*, it had
been buried before the חורבן הבית *Churban HaBayit* so it would not
get taken away and it was hidden somewhere under the בית המקדש
Beit HaMikdash *Beit HaMikdash*. Okay, so let's take a look at the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara*. תני Tani, *Tani*, השופרות האלו *hashofrot ha'elu*, these שופרות
*shofars* which we're going to find out in later משניות *Mishnayot* they
would people would come and they'd put money in for different קרבנות
*korbanot* and different purposes. עקומות היו *Akumot hayu*, they were bent. צרות
מלמעלה ורחבות מלמטה *Tzarot milmala v'rechavot milmata*, and they were sort of
pyramidal, narrow at the top and wide at the bottom. פני הרמאיים
*Pnei haramai'in* for the in order to protect against the deceivers or
the cheats. So you put in a little slot in the top,
you can't stick your hand in to get the money out, it's
very narrow at the top, also it might be bent like if
you imagine the money goes down like a curved type of a
thing, you know, so you certainly can't stick something in and pull
it out right if it's curved, you know, so anyway, okay. So
okay. תני tani, בשם רבי
אליעזר *Tani beshem Rabbi Eliezer*. Now that's all we had to say
about the שופרות *shofrot*, we'll see more about the שופרות *shofrot* later.
Now you get the fun opportunity, now you get the opportunity to
talk about the ארון aron *Aron*. הארון גלה עמהם לבבל *Ha'aron gala
imahem l'Bavel*. The ארון aron *Aron* was not hidden under the בית
המקדש Beit Hamikdash *Beit HaMikdash*, it was taken into exile in בבל
Bavel. *Bavel* with all the rest of the vessels of the בית
המקדש Beit HaMikdash *Beit HaMikdash*. We're not talking about the stuff on
the ark that was בית שני *Bayit Sheni*, we're talking about בית
ראשון *Bayit Rishon*. Okay. מאי טעמא mai ta'ama? *Mai taama*, לא יותר
דבר אמר amar, ה׳ *lo yivater davar amar Hashem*. Nothing will be
left, said the Lord. אין דבר *Ein davar*, אין דבר *ein davar*
and what does דבר *davar* mean? אלא ella, שדברות לתוכו *Ela shedibrot
letocho*, the דבר *davar*, the דיבור dibbur. *dibor*, the דברות *dibrot*, the
עשרת הדברות aseret ha-dibrot. *Aseret HaDibrot*. So the things that had the
עשרת הדברות *Aseret HaDibrot*, that won't be left behind, even that is
taken into exile.
וכן הוא אומר omer *V'chen hu omer* and
similarly it says בתשובת השנה שלח המלך נבוכדנצר ויביאהו בבל Bavel, *bitshuvat
hashana shelach hamelech Nevuchadnezzar v'yevi'ehu Bavel*, and at the end of the
year the king נבוכדנצר *Nevuchadnezzar* sent and he brought the king of
Israel to בבל *Bavel* עם כלי kli, חמדת בית ה׳ *im klei
chemdat Beit Hashem*, with the vessels of the the desirous vessels of
the house of the house of God. איזו כלי חמדת בית ה׳
*Eizu klei chemdat Beit Hashem*, what is the vessels that are desirous
of the house of the Lord? What's the most desirous vessel? זה
zeh הארון *Zeh ha'aron*, it's the ארון aron. *Aron*. So you see
according to this the ארון aron. *Aron* was taken with all the
rest of the vessels into בבל *Bavel*. But תיובתא *tiyuvta* again the
משנה Mishnah *Mishna*, that's a ברייתא braita, *Baraita*. Okay. ריש לקיש Resh
Lakish אומר omer *Reish Lakish omer*, במקומו היה הארון נגנז *bimkomo haya
ha'aron nignaz*. No, it was hidden in its place meaning under the
קודש הקדשים *Kodesh HaKodashim*. Okay, that's where it was put away, that's
where it was hidden. הדא הוא דכתיב hada hu de-chtiv, *Hadhu dichtiv*,
that's what's meant by the verse. ויאריכו הבדים ויראו ראשי הבדים מן
man הקודש על פני הדביר ולא יראו החוצה *Vayarichu habadim vayira'u rashei
habadim min hakodesh al pnei hadevir v'lo yira'u hachutza*. And what does
that have to say? It says that the posts, you know, of
the ארון aron *Aron* extended so the face of, you know, by
the face of the דביר *devir*, the דביר *devir* is the קודש
הקדשים *Kodesh HaKodashim* and they cannot be seen outside. דכתיב di-chtiv *Dichtiv*
and the verse says okay ולא יראו החוצה *v'lo yira'u hachutza*. Now
how does that how does that prove it? Because the end of
the פסוק Pasuk *pasuk* is ויהיו שם עד היום הזה ad hayom
hazeh. *vayiheyu sham ad hayom hazeh*, I think is the according to
the בית *bet*. No, somebody quotes it, the קרבן העדה *Korban HaEdah*
says the end of the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* is oh ולא יראו
*v'lo yira'u*... ויהיו שם עד היום הזה *vayiheyu sham ad hayom hazeh*
is the end of the פסוק pasuk, *pasuk* and it was there
until this very day. Now obviously the simple sense is until this
very day that the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* was being written in מלכים
*Melachim* which was when there was still a בית המקדש הראשון *Beit
HaMikdash HaRishon* but they're reading עד היום הזה *ad hayom hazeh* means
up until whenever you're going to read this פסוק pasuk *pasuk*, up
until today that's where the ארון aron *Aron* is. So if the
ארון aron *Aron* is anywhere it's buried under the קודש הקדשים *Kodesh
HaKodashim*. That's that proof. Okay, now since we quoted this פסוק pasuk
*pasuk*, נו *nu*, since we quoted this פסוק pasuk *pasuk*, the beginning
of the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* says that it's ויראו *vayera'u*, they were
seen, and then it says ולא יראו החוצה *v'lo yira'u hachutza*, they
weren't seen. So how do you how do you reconcile it? דכתיב
di-chtiv ויראו *Dichtiv vayera'u*, they were seen, ואת אמרת ולא יראו *ve'at
amarta v'lo yira'u*, so how does the end of the verse say
they weren't seen? אלא נראים ולא נראים *Ela nirim v'lo nirim*. They
were seen but they weren't fully seen. בולטים ויוצאים כשני דדי האשה
*Boltim v'yotzim kishnei dadei ha'isha*. They were protruding like a woman's breasts
which means that they were pointing into the curtain that separated it,
the פרוכת *parochet*, thank you, but you didn't actually see the בדים
*badim* but you could see their form because of the way they
protruded.
That's in general picks up on other types of of sexual and
erotic imagery that sometimes you have in relation to the ארון, aron
you know, and the כרובים. Kruvim. Or nurturing, that's true, but it's
also, there's also something that's also sort of erotic as well, you
know, it speaks about the כרובים Kruvim that they were intertwined like
lovers. So you have that theme here, alluded to here.
Okay, but that—the reason for the פסוק pasuk. quoting was the end
of it, which is עד היום הזה. Okay, so that's another theme.
רבנן אמי Rabbanan amei and the rabbis say, and this is the
position in the משנה, Mishnah. בלשכת העצים היה ארון גנוז, Belishkat ha'etzim
hayah Aron ganuz, it was hidden underneath in the room where they
kept the wood.
Any particular reason for that?
No, that's just a tradition. No verse is quoted. מעשה בכהן אחד,
Ma'aseh bechohen echad, there's a story with one כהן, Kohen בעל מום,
ba'al mum, he was—he had a blemish, so they couldn't actually have
him do the עבודה. avodah. So, you know, they put him to
work in something that was not the עבודה. avodah. שהיה עומד ומפצל
עצים בלשכת העצים, Shehayah omed umefatzel etzim belishkat ha'etzim, he was given
the job of peeling the wood, the bark off of the wood,
you know, and cleaning the wood in the room where they kept
the wood. It's like peeling potatoes, right? So nobody—nobody enjoys that job,
but that was his job, he had a מום. mum. He couldn't
do the
עבודה. avodah. וראה את הרצפה, Vera'ah et haritzpah, and he saw the
floor, שהיא משונה מחברותיה, shehi meshunah machavroteiha, and in one place it
was a little different than where it looked elsewhere. בא ואמר לחברו,
Ba ve'amar lachaveiro, he went and he told his friend, בוא ראה
את הרצפה הזאת שהיא משונה מחברותיה, Bo re'eh et haritzpah hazot shehi
meshunah machavroteiha, come and look, this section of floor looks different than
the other section. ולא הספיק לגמור את הדבר, Velo hispik ligmor et
hadavar, he didn't finish it, he didn't actually get to show him
where it was that—where it—you know, where the floor looked different, עד
שיצתה נשמתו, ad sheyatzata nishmato, he dropped dead.
He just found it out.
What? Now they could find it out. You wonder, like now they
could still find it out, they just inspect. But you know, it's
like one of those secrets where somebody finds the hidden passageway that
nobody's ever found in many, many years. So somehow, I don't know,
you had to do something to not notice. Maybe you had to
look very, very closely to see the subtle changes. וידעו בייחוד, Veyadu
beyichud, and they knew with certainty, ששם ארון גנוז, shesham Aron ganuz,
which is basically the story in our משנה. Mishnah. What? Certain.
And where can a
בעל מום ba'al mum not go?
What? Where can a בעל מום ba'al mum not go?
Because—that's a whole issue. There's like in places in the עזרה azarah
maybe, but—but this is—but this was not the עזרה azarah at all.
Okay. תני, we taught in a ברייתא, braita רבי אושעיא, Rabbi Oshaya,
הקישו
עליה בקורנס. Hikishu aleiha bekurnas. Now, they—bangs—ah, now, here's sort of like
Michael's suggestion. Well, look, if you know it's under the דיר העצים,
Deir Ha'etzim, why don't you
just—why don't you just try to dig up the floor of the
דיר העצים, Deir Ha'etzim, and then you can discover where the ארון
aron is. So he says, okay, here's a ברייתא braita, which הקישו
עליה בקורנס, hikishu aleiha bekurnas, they banged on the floor with like
a—who—hikishu, who's them?
Is it the—that's the—that did it? Or?
No, but it means someone. I don't think anyone in particular. Anyway,
with a קורנס kurnas is like—like what are those big things you
do to break ground? What are those called? Like—not a hammer. Yeah,
not a jackhammer. Like—anyway, whatever. Sledgehammer, that's what I was thinking about.
Anyway, some type of a hammer. What? Jack? Jack? Pickaxe? Okay. Is
that how they translated it or? No, that's no—pickaxe would work, yeah.
I think קורנס kurnas is a little bit more like a big
hammer. Whatever it is, anyway, they banged on it, maybe they found
the—maybe I said he didn't get to say where it was. Maybe
he did say where it was. Maybe—anyway, but whatever, as long as
they knew it was in the דיר העצים, they started banging around
and trying to dig it up. ויצא אש ושרפתו. Veyatza esh vesarfato.
Oh, so maybe Michael is right, maybe it's the same guy and
it's giving a different version of how he died. Yeah, you could
be right. I thought it meant other people, but you could be
right. Anyway, so he tried to dig up that place and a
fire came out. It's like straight out of Indiana Jones and Temple
of Doom. So they're trying to find the lost star—oh my god,
it's got all these booby traps. Okay, so anyway,
so they hit it on the floor and a fire came out
and burned him. תני רבי יהודה בן לקיש, Tani Rabbi Yehuda ben
Lakish, תני, it says in a ברייתא, braita רבי יהודה בן לקיש
Rabbi Yehuda ben Lakish אמר, amar funny that this is a ברייתא
beraisa. that has רבי יהודה בן לקיש, Rabbi Yehuda ben Lakish, really—anyway,
I don't know. Anyway,
שני ארונות היו מהלכין עם ישראל במדבר, Shnei aronot hayu mehalchin im
Yisrael bamidbar, there were two ארונות aronot that went with them in
the desert, in the wilderness. אחד שהיתה תורה נתונה בתוכו, Echad shehayetah
Torah netunah betocho, one that they put the תורה, Torah, and just—version
of the תורה Torah means the לוחות. Luchot. ואחד שהיו שברי לוחות
נתונין בתוכו, Ve'echad shehayu shivrei luchot netunin betocho, and a different one
that they kept the שברי לוחות. shivrei luchot. זה zeh, שהייתה—now, why
is he saying this? Because he's trying to reconcile a contradiction in
פסוקים. psukim זה zeh
שהייתה—by the way, it's also difficult because what did they do with
the שברי לוחות shivrei luchot. right—while they were waiting to build the
משכן, Mishkan, right? And so there—if you read the פסוקים psukim closely,
you will see there is a little confusion of exactly when was
the ארון, aron was there one ארון, aron was there two ארונות?
aronot? So he says this is not—you know, this actually, there's a
reason in the פסוקים psukim for this to make this assertion and
that there were two ארונות, aronot, one with the לוחות Luchot and
one with the שברי לוחות. shivrei luchot,
זה שהייתה תורה נתונה בתוכו היה מונח באוהל מועד, Zeh shehayetah Torah
netunah betocho hayah munach be'ohel mo'ed, the one with the לוחות Luchot
was within the אוהל מועד. Ohel Mo'ed. הדא הוא דכתיב וארון ברית
ה' ומשה לא משו מקרב המחנה. Hada hu daktiv va'aron berit Hashem
uMoshe lo mashu mikerev hamachaneh. Remember when they went to war and
they said after the מרגלים, meraglim, it says the ארון aron and
משה Moshe did not move from the camp, they stayed in the
camp, okay, which means it stayed in the אוהל. ohel. We'll see
why that's said to contrast this with the next line.
וזה שהיו שברי לוחות נתונין בתוכו, Vezeh shehayu shivrei luchot netunin betocho,
the one with the broken לוחות, Luchot, היה נכנס ויוצא עמהן, hayah
nichnas veyotze imahen, that would come and go with them, meaning when
they would travel and also for war. ופעמים שהיה מתראה עמהן, Upe'amim
shehayah mitra'eh imahen, and sometimes that was Sometimes it would be seen
with them like basically you know when they were out for war.
And we'll see why because the פסוק pasuk says, some actually quote
the פסוק, pasuk I don't see it here. Anyway, which is what
does the פסוק pasuk say? קומה ה' ויפוצו. Kuma Hashem ve-yafutzu. And
there's another פסוק pasuk. which says,
וארון ברית ה' נוסע לפניהם לתור להם מנוחה, Ve-aron brit Hashem nose'a
lifnehem latur lahem menucha, that the ארון aron, went in front of
them. So what's the story? Did the ארון aron. go in front
of them or was it carried with בני קהת Bnei Kehat and
did it stay in the camp and did it go in the
middle of the מחנה, machaneh, right, like it sounds like? So he
says no, the one with the שברי לוחות, shivrei luchot that went
in front of them לתור להם מנוחה, latur lahem menucha, and that
was the one that they took out with them to war. And
that's why when they went to war, you know, when they tried
to go into the land
after the מרגלים, meraglim, it says ומשה וארון ברית ה' לא משו
מקרב המחנה. u-moshe ve-aron brit Hashem lo mashu mi-kerev ha-machaneh. So anyway,
so there's one that went out with them to war and there's
one that stayed, you know, in the מקדש mikdash and traveled in
the center of the מחנה. machaneh. Okay, so he says that there
were two.
Now רבנן אמרי, Rabbanan amri, the Rabbis say, ארון אחד היה, Aron
echad haya, there was only one ארון. aron Right, so some have
that גרסא, girsa, the הגר"א G'ra actually quotes the פסוק pasuk וארון
ברית ה', ve-aron brit Hashem, I think that's the הגר"א G'ra's גרסא.
girsa. Hold on, let me take a look here at the
ג'. gimmel. אחד שהיו לוחות נתונות בתוכו, Echad she-hayu luchot netunot betokho,
זה שהיו לוחות, zeh she-hayu luchot, זה שהיו שברי לוחות היה נכנס
ויוצא
עמהם.
zeh she-hayu shivrei luchot
haya nichnas ve-yotzei imahem.
Okay no, that's something else. Anyway, some quote the
פסוק pasuk וארון ברית ה' נוסע לפניהם, ve-aron brit Hashem nose'a lifnehem,
which would very much fit in here. Okay, so now the גמרא
Gemara, continues.
ורבנן אמרי ארון אחד היה, Verabbanan amri aron echad haya, there was
only one ארון. aron? פעם אחת יצא בימי עלי דנשבה, Pa'am achat
yatza bimei Eli demishba, only once did it go out with them
to war at the time of עלי, Eli, and it was taken
captive. That was an exception, that was not the rule. Okay, so
we know they did take it out to war at the time
of עלי Eli and it was taken captive by the פלשתים. Plishtim.
And the question is does that demonstrate what they usually did or
was that an exception? And the Rabbis say that was an exception.
קרא מסייע להו לרבנן. Kraya misaye'a lehu lerabbanan. A פסוק pasuk supports
the Rabbis. אוי לנו מי יצילנו מיד האלהים האדירים האלה. Oy lanu
mi yatzilenu miyad ha-elohim ha-adirim ha-eleh. When it was taken out at
the time of עלי, Eli, what did the פלשתים Plishtim say? They
said, אוי לנו מי יצילנו מיד האלהים האדירים האלה, oy lanu mi
yatzilenu miyad ha-elohim ha-adirim ha-eleh, who will save us from the hands
of this great God? So it sounds like it was an astonishing
thing that the ארון aron was being brought out. מילא דלא חמון
מיומיהון, Mila d'lo chamun mi-yomeihon, it's a thing that they had never
seen in their days, the ארון aron being brought out.
And only then did they say it. What do you mean? Because
like with דגון Dagon and all that?
No, no, no, that was afterwards. No, I think
that when they saw the ארון Aron initially, this was their response.
You can check the פסוק. pasuk, Okay, so it seems like they
had never had that happen to them before that the ארון Aron,
was brought out and as soon as they saw it they all
of a sudden were struck with fear.
Terrified. Terrified, right.
קרא מסייע לרבי יהודה בן לקיש.
Kraya
misaye'a le-Rabbi Yehuda ben Lakish.
So that shows it was an exception. A פסוק pasuk supports רבי
יהודה בן לקיש Rabbi Yehuda ben Lakish that it was a regular
thing. רבי יהודה בן לקיש, Rabbi Yehuda ben Lakish, ויאמר שאול לאחיה
הגישה ארון האלהים. vayomer Sha'ul le-Achiya hagisha aron ha-elohim. So he shows
it to אחיה. Achiya. הגישה ארון האלהים, hagisha aron ha-elohim, bring forth
the ארון Aron of God. והלא ארון בקרית יערים היה. Ve-halo aron
be-Kiryat Ye'arim haya. What do you mean? The ארון Aron, was in
קרית יערים, Kiryat Ye'arim, it was that's where the פסוק pasuk says
it had been until that time. So
what was שאול Sha'ul assuming that the ארון Aron was there? Must
be that there was a separate ארון Aron that went with them
to war. מה עבדו להו רבנן הגישה אלי? Ma avdu lehu rabbanan
hagisha elai? So how do the Rabbis explain this פסוק pasuk of
הגישה אלי? hagisha elai? הציץ. Ha-tzitz. That's not really the ארון, Aron
it's the ציץ. tzitz. Not exactly clear why the ציץ tzitz is
called the ארון. Aron I mean but the same certain idea that
somehow it carries God's word with it, you know, and the ציץ
tzitz is the form of...
הגישה ארון האלהים, hagisha aron ha-elohim, how do you say that's the
ציץ?
tzitz? I have no idea. The מפרשים mefarshim say it maybe it
means just a box that had in it the, you know, the
vessels of God, but it's a very hard read. I have no
idea. I mean maybe it functioned similarly in that it somehow carried
the word of God in it, but how it's referred to ארון
Aron I have no idea. Anyway, so that's obviously a challenging פסוק.
pasuk. קרא מסייע לרבי יהודה בן לקיש. Kraya misaye'a le-Rabbi Yehuda ben
Lakish. Another פסוק pasuk supports רבי יהודה בן לקיש Rabbi Yehuda ben
Lakish that there were two ארונות. aronot. הארון וישראל ויהודה יושבים בסוכות.
Ha-aron ve-Yisrael ve-Yehuda yoshvim basukkot. What does אוריה Uriya say when דוד
David tells him go back and sleep with your wife? He says
how can I go back and sleep with my wife?
הארון וישראל ויהודה, ha-aron ve-Yisrael ve-Yehuda, they're all in their tents out
there at the battlefield. So it sounds like where's the ארון? Aron,
With them on the battlefield, right? He says הארון וישראל ויהודה יושבים
בסוכות. ha-aron ve-Yisrael ve-Yehuda yoshvim basukkot. So he says והלא ארון בציון
היה. ve-halo aron be-Tzion haya. The ארון Aron. was in ציון, Tzion,
that's where I mean they didn't have a בית המקדש yet but
that's where it had been moved. So what does he mean it's
out there in a tent? So מה עבדו להו רבנן? ma avdu
lehu rabbanan? How do the Rabbis explain it? So it means סכך,
skhakh, שהוא כקירוי. she-hu ke-kirui. It doesn't mean סוכות, sukkot, it means
that it's in a it means that it's not like in a
tent out on the battlefield. Yes, it's wherever housing it is in
in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, but it's not in a permanent house. We don't
have a בית המקדש yet. So he called it סוכות sukkot to
refer to like an impermanent place, not to literally mean that it's
out there in a tent on the battlefield. שעדיין לא נבנה בית
הבחירה.
she-adayin
lo nivna beit ha-bechira.
Yes, I know, which is why it was a good proof for
רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. Okay, but the simple sense is they're all
out there on the battlefield. But he reads no, no, no, ישראל
Yisrael's on the battlefield, the ארון Aron, is in an impermanent house,
I'm supposed to go sleep with my wife? Okay, so anyway there
are nice פסוקים psukim. that support at least in נ"ך, Nach, it's
not so clearly in the תורה. Torah. that support this idea that
there might have been a separate ארון Aron. that they took with
them to war. משנגנז הארון, Mishenignaz ha-Aron, now
so that was an interesting discussion about was there one or two
ארונות. aronot. Now, משנגנז הארון, mishenignaz ha-Aron, now we're going to talk
about the fact that it was hidden. We seen a discussion where
was it hidden and maybe it wasn't hidden at all, maybe it
was taken into בבל. From the time that it was hidden, נגנז
עמו צנצנת המן, nignaz imo tzintzenet ha-man,
the you know sort of the container of the מן man right
because it says קח צנצנת אחת והנח אותה לפני העדות למשמרת, kach
tzintzenet achat vehanach otah lifnei ha-edut lemishmeret, right? למשמרת, lemishmeret, right? So
you take a container of מן man. and it was kept there
for a safekeeping or for a memorial. So if that was עמו,
imo, if that was, you know, that's placed with the ארון, Aron
the assumption is whatever happened with the ארון aron. happened to the
מן. So, וצלוחית שמן המשחה u-tzlochit shemen ha-mishchah and the שמן המשחה
shemen ha-mishchah that they used to anoint, we're going to have a
discussion about the שמן המשחה, shemen ha-mishchah, right, that they used to
anoint, that also was with the ארון, aron? because it says by
the שמן המשחה shemen ha-mishchah it says שמן משחת קודש יהיה זה
לי לדורותיכם shemen mishchat kodesh yihyeh zeh li ledoroteichem
and by the צנצנת המן tzintzenet ha-man it says למשמרת לדורותיכם. lemishmeret
ledoroteichem.
So they make a היקש hekesh connection between the two that both
of them were somehow kept together and kept with the ארון aron,
and therefore the assumption is that when the ארון Aron, was buried
or hidden these were hidden with it. ומקלו של אהרן ופרחיו ושקדיו
u-maklo shel Aharon u-frachav u-shkedav
okay and the staff of אהרן Aharon and its blossoms and its
almonds, presumably wherever the staff went, there went the blossoms and the
almonds, okay, but anyway, but they say by the staff of אהרן
Aharon as well the פסוק pasuk says, you know, put it, you
know, לפני העדות למשמרת, lifnei ha-edut lemishmeret, right.
So again, so again the assumption is it's with the ארון aron,
and it is there as a משמרת mishmeret and whatever happens to
the ארון aron, happens to it. למשמרת לאות לבני מרי, lemishmeret le'ot
livnei meri,
so again everything here is למשמרת. lemishmeret. So to be a משמרת
mishmeret it has to be around forever, so it's hidden as well.
Okay, and now not only that, וארגז ששיגרו פלשתים אשם לאלהי ישראל
ve-argaz she-shigru Plishtim asham l'Elohei Yisrael
and when the פלשתים Plishtim at the end of the story we
quoted before took the ארון aron, and then all this plague happened
to them and then they returned the ארון, aron, they returned it
with a, you know, with a box filled with a gift and
it says by that box it says what does it say by
the box? The פסוק pasuk
says oh, תשימו בארגז מצדו. tasimu ba-argaz mitzido.
So when they return it it says they say put this in
the box next to the ארון. aron. So it's quite interesting. Since
the פלשתים Plishtim say next to the ארון, aron. the assumption is
it always remains next to the ארון. aron It's getting pretty crowded
there in the קדש הקדשים. Kodesh Hakodashim. Okay. Okay, now מי גנזו?
mi genazo? Now we get back to it being hidden. Who hid
it? יאשיהו גנזו. Yoshiyahu genazo. Now not only where was it hidden,
but wherever it was hidden, assuming it was hidden, who did it?
So it was יאשיהו Yoshiyahu towards the end of מלכי ישראל malchei
Yisrael but not at the very end. But he already had enough
of a sense of what was coming up. כיוון שראה שכתוב, keivan
sher'ah shekatuv, he saw the verse said יולך ה' אותך ואת מלכך
אשר תקים עליך אל גוי אשר לא ידעת אתה ואבותיך, yolech Hashem
otcha ve'et malkecha asher takim alecha el goy asher lo yadata atah
va'avotecha, the verse prophesying the exile, God will take you and your
king to a nation that you did not know. עמד וגנזו, amad
u-genazo, he went and he hid it. He sort of saw the
writing on the wall. הדא הוא דכתיב, hada hu de-chtiv, that was
Daniel, הדא הוא דכתיב, hada hu dichtiv, that's what's meant by the
פסוק, pasuk ויאמר ללוים המבינים לכל ישראל הקדושים לה' תנו את ארון
הקודש בבית אשר בנה שלמה בן דויד מלך ישראל אין לכם
משא בכתף, vayomer laleviyim hamevinim lechol Yisrael hakedoshim l'Hashem tnu et aron
hakodesh babayit asher banah Shlomo ben David melech Yisrael ein lachem masa
bakatef, put the ארון aron. in the house that דויד David
built, no longer will carry it on the shoulder. So what does
it mean אין לכם משא בכתף? ein lachem masa bakatef? They've been
carrying on the shoulder for centuries, right? Why what does he mean
put it in the בית? So אמר להם, amar lahem, this is
what he means. He basically means hide it under the בית, that's
how we're reading it. אם גולה הוא עמכם לבבל, im goleh hu
imachem le-Vavel, if this would be exiled with you to בבל, אין
אתם מחזירים אותו עוד למקומו, ein atem machzirim oto od limkomo, you
will no longer have an opportunity to bring it back. So אין
לכם משא בכתף ein lachem masa bakatef did not just refer to
the biblical period when they would carry it on the shoulder, but
he meant this is no longer going to be transported back, you
won't have an opportunity to transport it back so you better hide
it now underneath the בית המקדש so we don't lose it when
the eventual exile comes. אלא עתה עבדו את ה' אלהיכם ואת עמו
ישראל.
ela
atah
ivdu et Hashem Eloheichem ve'et amo Yisrael.
Now serve ה' Hashem your God and his nation and his nation
ישראל. Yisrael.
Come on that פסוק pasuk is the proof in... what? Did they
unearth... no he doesn't buy in he doesn't believe the whole thing.
What do you mean? It's just a rabbinic מדרש midrash read into
the פסוקים. Okay this assumes that it was hidden. Okay.
Now, now since he mentioned the שמן המשחה, shemen ha-mishchah, we're going
to have a nice little digression to talk about the שמן המשחה.
shemen ha-mishchah. So let's take a look. פיטום שמן המשחה, pitum shemen
ha-mishchah, now the making of the שמן המשחה, shemen ha-mishchah, it
says ואתה קח לך בשמים ראש מר דרור חמש מאות וקנמן בשם
מחציתו חמשים ומאתים וקנה בשם חמשים ומאתים וקדה חמש
מאות בשקל הקודש ושמן זית הין. ve'atah kach lecha besamim rosh mor
dror chamesh me'ot u-kinman besem machtzito chamishim u-matayim u-kneh bosem chamishim u-matayim
u-kidah chamesh me'ot beshekel hakodesh veshemen zayit hin. So if you add
up all of the various fragrances that were mentioned שהן אלף וחמש
מאות מנין,
she-hen elef u-chamesh me'ot
manin, it's
1,500 just adding up the things mentioned in the פסוק pasuk מנה,
maneh, which is like a significant measure of these fragrances. All of
these like you know whatever huge amount of fragrances right in the
פסוק pasuk with a הין hin 12 לוג log of olive oil.
You know how much 12 לוג... log... 144 whatever, 28, 168 ounces
something, right? Gallon and a
half. That amount of olive oil for fifteen hundred
מנה, maneh, I don't know exactly how much a מנה maneh is,
but it's not insignificant, of these fragrances. Okay, so how exactly does
that work? So that's what we're going to discuss. All of this
because we mentioned the שמן המשחה. shemen hamishcha. Okay, so let's take
a look.
שמן זית הין שנים עשר לוג, shemen zayis hin shneim asar log,
that was 12 log, שהיו שולקים בו את העיקרים, she-hayu sholkim bo
es ha-ikarim, what you would do with it is you would use
it to like
boil in it the עיקרים, ikarim, the roots of the fragrances. דברי
רבי מאיר, divrei Rabbi Meir, that's what Rabbi Meir would say said.
רבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda omer, Rabbi Yehuda said, שולקן היה במים,
sholkan haya bemayim, no, no, no, first you would boil them in
water to get them to absorb as much liquid as they could,
because if they start if they haven't already absorbed liquid, then the
oil gets absorbed into these, you know, into these fragrances and nothing
will come out.
ונותן שמן על גביהן, venosein shemen al gabeihen, then after they have
fully absorbed, then you put the oil on top of it and
it won't get absorbed into the fragrances, these and those have been
fully, you know, suffused with water, and what will happen is the
smell of the fragrances will transfer to the oil. משעה שקלט את
הריח, mishaa shekalat es hare'ach, then after the oil got absorbed the
fragrance, היה מעבירו, haya maaviro, then they would remove it from on
top of these, of these, you know,
herbs and these fragrances, and then they would have it and it
would have absorbed their smell.
כדרך שהפטמים עושים, kederech shehapitamim osim, and this is the way that
people that make fragrance, the perfumers do. הדא הוא דכתיב, di-chtiv that's
what's meant by the verse, שמן משחת קדש יהיה זה לי לדורותיכם.
shemen mishchas kodesh yihye zeh li ledoroseichem. Now what exactly he gets
from that verse of שמן משחת קדש shemen mishchas kodesh is not
exactly clear to me. We'll see, let me just see if any
says anything here.
No, the מפרשים meforshim don't say exactly what they mean to prove
by that פסוק. pasuk. Okay. תני רבי יהודה בר רבי אלעאי, tani
Rabbi Yehuda bar Rabbi Ilai, שמן המשחה שעשה משה במדבר, shemen hamishcha
sheasa Moshe bamidbar, מעשה נסים נעשו בו. maaseh nissim naasu vo. This
שמן המשחה shemen hamishcha that Moshe made in the wilderness, it was
miracles after miracles, מתחלה ועד סוף, mitchila ve'ad sof, from the beginning
to the end. שמתחלה לא היה בו אלא שנים עשר לוג, shemitchila
lo haya vo ela shneim asar log, it started with twelve log,
שנאמר שמן זית הין, shene'emar shemen zayis hin, okay, 12 so that
we said a הין hin is twelve לוג. log. אם לסוך בו
את העיקרים לא היה בו סיפק, im lasuch bo es ha-ikarim lo
haya vo sipeik, just to try to like use it to like
you know to anoint the fragrances, just to smear on the fragrances,
there's not enough 12 הין hin for that amount of fragrances. על
אחת כמה וכמה, al achas kama vechama, how much more so, what's
going to happen? שהאור בולע, sheha'or bolei'a, if you put it over
fire, the fire is going to absorb it, meaning cause it to
you know
evaporate. והעצים בולעים, veha'eitzim bol'im, the woods, meaning you know the fragrances
themselves will absorb the liquid. והיורה בולעת, ve-hayora bola'as, and some will
get absorbed by the pot. וממנו נמשחו המשכן, umimenu nimshachu hamishkan, and
so, number one, think how much you went down from your original
twelve הין hin just in the process of making it. Number two,
וממנו נמשחו המשכן, umimenu nimshachu hamishkan, and what did you do with
the oil? Used it to anoint the משכן Mishkan וכל כליו, vechol
kelav, of all the vessels, השלחן וכל כליו, hashulchan vechol kelav, המנורה
וכל כליה, hamenora vechol keleiha,
all the vessels, all the attendant vessels. וממנו נמשחו אהרן כהן גדול,
umimenu nimshachu Aharon Kohen Gadol,
and then you'd use it to anoint Aaron, ובניו, uvanav, and the
sons, כל שבעת ימי המילואים, kol shivas yemei hamilu'im, and you did
this every day of the seven days of the מילואים. milu'im. So
וממנו נמשחו כהנים גדולים ומלכים, umimenu nimshachu kohanim gedolim umelachim, and in
the from the future you would use it for future כהנים גדולים
kohanim gedolim and kings, actually we'll see about כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol.
Okay, and so think about the miracle about this, that you had
only twelve הין hin and it was able to do all of
this. Not only that, but the other point that's sort of being
alluded to, and that might have been why he quoted the פסוק
pasuk by שמן משחת קדש יהיה זה לי לדורותיכם, shemen mishchas kodesh
yihye zeh li ledoroseichem,
that the דרשה derasha is that זה in גימטריא gematria is 12.
So there's a famous מדרש Midrash which is זה, the 12, the
12 לוג log is לדורותיכם, ledoroseichem, that it always remains 12 לוג.
log. You started with 12 לוג log and it would always remain
12 לוג log in the whole process, and then you did all
this stuff, and not only did it still last, that there was
something left, but the full amount was still left. It was like
the נס חנוכה neis Chanukah every single time. Okay, so the full
amount of oil was always left afterwards.
So that's miracles from the very beginning to the end. And now
we're going to discuss what it was used for in the future
after the initial anointing. Okay. מלך בתחלה טעון משיחה. Melech betchila ta'un
meshicha.
When somebody initially becomes king, meaning basically David, required משיחה. meshicha. מלך
בן מלך אין טעון משיחה, Melech ben melech ein ta'un meshicha, but
the son of a king does not. But if you have, like,
you know, for example were you to have a, we'll see, somebody
who is not yeah, a revolution, but we'll see about that in
a minute, what if it's not from מלכי בית
דוד.
malchei
Beis David.
שאול Shaul also? Well, well,
that's true.
שאול Shaul also, thank you, pre-David as well. So שאול Shaul and
דוד. David. מאי טעמא? קום משחהו כי זה הוא. kum mishcha'ehu ki
zeh hu. Get up and anoint him, for this is the one.
זה טעון משיחה ואין בנו טעון משיחה. zeh ta'un meshicha ve'ein beno
ta'un meshicha.
Only he, not his son. אבל כהן גדול בן כהן גדול, Aval
Kohen Gadol ben Kohen Gadol, but a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol the
son of a כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, אפילו עד עשרה דורות afilu
ad asarah doros even ten generations, טעון משיחה taun meshichah will be,
because the basic difference is the following: the kingship is considered to
be a hereditary position, whereas כהן גדול Kohen Gadol is not fundamentally
hereditary. It does say that—well, כהן Kohen is, but כהן גדול Kohen
Gadol is not. It is true that there's a statement in הוריות
Horayos that the son gets preference, like all other things being equal
you would prefer to do it as the son of a כהן
גדול. Kohen Gadol. But having some preference does not mean that fundamentally
it's a hereditary position. So therefore each כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, even
the son, has to be newly invested into that status, whereas a
king is fundamentally hereditary. You don't need a new act of investing
him, he naturally gets it from the father. Now the question is:
what happens if there are multiple children and there's a question who
the heir is? We'll see. Because that's right, exactly. But that's the
reason why there is this—the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol son of a
כהן גדול Kohen Gadol does not—but does—but a king the son of
a king does not. Okay.
אפילו עד עשרה דורות טעון משיחה, afilu ad asara doros taun meshicha,
even if the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol has been handed down ten
generations, so it's been practiced as a hereditary position, but in principle
it is not a hereditary position. And therefore every time it requires
משיחה. meshicha. וכולו קיים לעתיד לבוא, vechulo kayam laatid lavo, and oh,
I jumped ahead, this is what it says. So think about all
of the generations, all of the ways it was
used, how much it should have evaporated in the process, how many
different vessels and things it was used for, and at the end
it will still be the full amount through the future. ההוא דכתיב,
hahu dechtiv, that's what's meant by the פסוק pasuk, שמן משחת קודש
יהיה זה לי לדורותיכם. shemen mishchas kodesh yihyeh zeh li ledoroseichem. So
either the דרשה drasha is סתם stam לדורותיכם, ledoroseichem, it'll always be
the same amount, but there's also a דרשה drasha that emphasizes the
זה גמטריא gematria 12, as another way
of emphasizing the miracle that it will always remain the full amount.
Okay. Now we're talking about using it for kings, so now we're
going to talk about kings. Let's take a look.
Anointing kings. אין מושחין את המלכים אלא על גבי המעיין.
ein moshchin es hamelachim
ela al gabei hamayan. When you anoint kings, which as we now
know is not going to be too often because you only do
it at the beginning of a kingship, of like a line, you
do it by a flowing water, by a wellspring. כנאמר, kene'emar, because
that's what we get by
שלמה. Shlomo. הרכיבתם את שלמה בני על הפרדה אשר לי והורדתם אותו
אל גיחון ומשח אותו שם צדוק הכהן ונתן הנביא למלך על ישראל.
harkivtem es Shlomo beni al hapirda asher li vehovardetem oso el Gichon
umashach oso sham Tzadok Hakohen veNasan Hanavi lemelech al Yisrael. And צדוק
Tzadok the כהן and נתן Nasan the נביא Navi will anoint him
as a king. Now, why did they anoint him? He was the
son of a king. So, let's—anyways, but there it was on a
wellspring, and we see that that somehow is indicative of how it
always should be. And the idea is, you know, as is explained
בבבלי, baBavli, that obviously symbolic, that the flowing of the water, that
his kingship should flow, it should be nurturing, it should give life,
and so on. אין מושחין מלך בן מלך אלא מפני המחלוקת. ein
moshchin melech ben melech ela mipnei hamachlokes. The only time you would
do the king the son of a king is if there's a
debate which is the heir. מפני מה נמשח שלמה? mipnei mah nimshach
Shlomo? So why was שלמה Shlomo anointed? מפני מחלוקתו של אדוניהו, mipnei
machlokso shel Adoniyahu, because אדוניהו Adoniyahu was competing for the kingship. יואש,
Yoash, why was יואש Yoash anointed? מפני עתליהו. mipnei Atalyahu. Now everybody
can test their תנ"ך Tanach if they know any of this. Okay.
יהואחז, Yehoachaz, I won't tell you how I get upset. יהואחז—מפני יהויקים.
Yehoyakim יהואחז Yehoachaz was anointed because יהויקים Yehoyakim was competing for it,
אחיו achiv his brother, שהיה גדול ממנו שתי שנים, shehayah gadol mimenu
shtei shanim, which is two years older than him. יהוא—מפני יורם. Yoram.
יהוא Yehu was anointed because of יורם. Yoram Okay. לאו כתיב קום
משחהו כי זה הוא. lav ksiv kum meshachehu ki zeh hu. זה
טעון—now zeh taun one minute.
So now the גמרא Gemara has a question. So that was the—that
was the ברייתא. beraisa. Okay, so when would we do the king
the son of a king, only when there's a debate. But now
the גמרא's Gemara got another question. The גמרא, Gemara how did we
have this last listing of יהוא Yehu מפני יורם, mipnei Yoram. that
was מלכי ישראל. Malchei Yisrael. And the גמרא's Gemara now going to
say that we would only anoint מלכי בית דוד, Malchei Beis David,
מלכי יהודה. Malchei Yehuda. Okay, now we haven't said it yet, but
now we're going to assert that. One minute. לאו כתיב, lav ksiv,
doesn't the פסוק pasuk say, קום משחהו כי זה הוא. kum meshachehu
ki zeh hu. זה טעון משיחה, zeh taun meshicha, this one, not
just this one because he's the first as what we said before,
but this one because he's from מלכי ישראל—מלכי יהודה. Yehuda, ואין מלכי
ישראל טעונין משיחה, ve'ein Malchei Yisrael teunin meshicha, but not מלכי ישראל.
Malchei Yisrael So why did you mention this יהוא Yehu and יורם
Yoram. thing? אלא, fine. יהואחז מפני יהויקים אחיו שהיה גדול ממנו שתי
שנים, Yehoachaz mipnei Yehoyakim achiv shehayah gadol mimenu shtei shanim, period. Meaning,
cut off the last words. You're right. We shouldn't have mentioned the
issue of the competition of יהוא Yehu and יורם. That was not
real—a משיחה meshicha done with the שמן המשחה shemen hamishcha because that
was מלכי ישראל. Malchei Yisrael. So cut those words out of the
ברייתא. Baraita Okay, fine. Now the גמרא Gemara says, one minute, I
got another question. And this explains—this last question is going to explain
why we went to this whole big digression about שמן המשחה shemen
hamishcha in this conversation about hiding the ארון. aron, Because here's our
question now. So the גמרא says like this. ולא יאשיהו גנזו? velo
Yoshiyahu genazo? One minute. Didn't you tell me at the beginning of
the דף that יאשיהו Yoshiyahu hid the שמן המשחה shemen hamishcha with
the ארון? aron If יאשיהו Yoshiyahu hid the ארון, aron. he hid
the שמן המשחה. shemen hamishcha. But one minute. But this—but this here
thing about—what do you call
it? About... How could יאשיהו Yoshiyahu have hid the ארון, aron, hid
the שמן המשחה, Shemen Hamishcha, and now we're saying that it was
used for יהויקים Yehoyakim and יהואחז? Yehoachaz So the גמרא says, והלא
יאשיהו גנזו? vehalo Yoshiyahu genazo? Didn't יאשיהו Yoshiyahu do it? Hide it?
So you know what? אדא אמר, Ada amar, you're right. באפרסמון נמשח.
Bafarsimon nimshach. You're right. So the יהויקים and יהואחז Yehoachaz? was not
with the שמן המשחה. Shemen Hamishcha. That was just with aromatic oil.
They did not do it with the real שמן המשחה. Shemen Hamishcha.
And some of the מפרשים meforshim say, and now we don't have
to edit out the last part of the ברייתא about יהוא Yehu
either, because that could be referring to aromatic oil. Meaning you could
maintain the idea of doing an anointing of kings even without the
שמן המשחה Shemen Hamishcha when you don't have it, and that would
then give us the latitude to do it for מלכי ישראל Malchei
Yisrael. as well. Okay, but even then we would only do it
when there was some issue of debate and uncertainty about who was
going to inherit it, or else we wouldn't do it because you
don't want, in a way, you don't want to undermine the sense
of it as a hereditary position. So you don't need to reaffirm
it. It would in a way weaken it to reaffirm it when
it's not necessary. But you would do something when there was a
debate, and if there was no שמן המשחה, Shemen Hamishcha, you'd use
this, you know, you'd just use aromatic oil. Okay. So now that
we're talking about the שמן המשחה Shemen Hamishcha and the use of
it for כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, you don't use it for kings
unless you have to, now we're going to have a little bit
more about the שמן המשחה. Shemen Hamishcha. So let's take a look.
אין מושחין המלכים אלא מן הקרן. Ein moshchin hamelakhim ela min hakeren.
When you anoint kings, you do it from a horn, again, the
same idea of like a cornucopia, right, the sense of plenty, or
maybe the sense also of proclamation and announcement. Okay. שאול ויהוא נמשכו
מן הפך.
Shaul veYehu nimshakhu
min hapakh. שאול Shaul and יהוא Yehu that were anointed from a
simple like just a pitcher, היתה מלכותם מלכות עוברת. hayta malkhutam malkhut
overet. Theirs was only a temporary, an ephemeral kingship. דוד ושלמה נמשכו
מן הקרן. David uShlomo nimshakhu min hakeren. They were anointed from a
horn, היתה מלכותם מלכות קיימת, hayta malkhutam malkhut kayyamet, and it lasted.
He says, מצמיח קרן ישועה. matzmiach keren yeshua.
מצמיח קרן
ישועה,
matzmiach
keren
yeshua, thank you very much, right,
his status, so it's connected to the saving power of the sovereign.
Right, thank you very much, מצמיח קרן ישועה, matzmiach keren yeshua, that's,
yes, very much that symbolism. אין מושחין כהנים מלכים. Ein moshchin kohanim
melakhim. Now you don't make כהנים Kohanim into kings. Now, why not?
So well, first of all, the thing of course to appreciate is
the whole issue of the חשמונאים. Chashmonaim. So it's not actually saying
that you don't allow כהנים Kohanim to serve as kings, although we
sort of will say that in a minute. Right now it's focusing
the issue on the issue of משיחה, meshikha, and that might be
the assumption that משיחה meshikha is the same way it's limited to
מלכות יהודה, malkhut Yehuda, is limited to מלכות בית דוד. malkhut Beit
David. Then it's not really about the כהנים, Kohanim, then really it's
a problem about anybody who's not מלכות בית דוד. malkhut Beit David.
Okay, but obviously there's a different, a unique problem about the כהנים,
Kohanim, which is the joining of the religious and the political leadership,
which can be very dangerous as, whatever, we have some indication nowadays.
So אין מושחין כהנים מלכים. ein moshchin kohanim melakhim. You do not
make כהנים, Kohanim, you don't, you do not anoint them as kings.
אמר רבי יהודה אנטונדריא, Amar Rabbi Yehuda Antundaraya, interesting name, על שם
לא יסור שבט מיהודה. al shem lo yasur shevet miYehuda. The kingship
shall never turn away from יהודה, so that it cannot be by
any other tribe. Again, since we're, since we're now ראש חודש כסלו,
Rosh Chodesh Kislev, we're in the period of חנוכה, Chanukah, I should
mention that the רמב"ן Ramban says that if you notice it, there
is no משנה Mishna, that talks about the מצווה mitzvah of חנוכה,
Chanukah, that talks about the חג chag of חנוכה. Chanukah. It's mentioned
in one משנה Mishna. in passing in בבא קמא Bava Kamma that
talks about if a guy has his donkey or whatever, his camel
carrying flax, and it passes by somebody else's store that has a
light, and the, and it lights the flax, who's liable? And it
says, well, if it was a חנוכה Chanukah lamp, then the store
owner isn't liable because he should have had that out there. That
is the one place חנוכה Chanukah is mentioned in the משנה. So
he says, what's going on? Like we have a whole מסכת פורים,
masekhet Purim, a whole מסכת מגילה masekhet Megillah on פורים, Purim, why
don't we have anything on חנוכה? Chanukah? So he says, you know,
the תנאים Tana'im were upset at the חשמונאים Chashmonaim because they shouldn't
have chosen, they shouldn't have made themselves into kings. And especially if
you see that רבי יהודה הנשיא Rabbi Yehuda HaNasi saw himself as
being a descendant of דוד המלך. David HaMelekh. So he said that
that's why they were sort of given the silent treatment in the
משנה. He says the חז"ל Chazal were not happy with the way
the חשמונאים Chashmonaim chose to take upon themselves the kingship. Alright, so
here's saying this, eluding to a similar type of a theme, לא
יסור שבט מיהודה. lo yasur shevet miYehuda.
Anyway, the רמב"ן Ramban says in his commentary on the פסוק pasuk
of לא יסור שבט מיהודה. lo yasur shevet miYehuda. Okay. אמר רבי
חייא בר אבא, Amar Rabbi Chiyya bar Abba, למען יאריך ימים על
ממלכתו הוא ובניו בקרב ישראל. lema'an yaarikh yamim al mamlakhto hu uvanav
bekerev Yisrael. Here's another verse that's specific about the כהנים. Kohanim. When
it speaks about the king, it says, you know, this is what
he should do, he should have the ספר תורה, Sefer Torah, that
his kingship should extend, he and his children. מה כתיב בתריה? Mah
ketiv batrei? What does the next פסוק say right afterwards? לא יהיה
לכהנים הלויים. Lo yihyeh lakohanim halevi'im. Now the end of it is
כל שבט לוי חלק ונחלה עם אחיו, kol shevet Levi chelek venachala
im achav, right, but the point is juxtaposed to kingship is not
for the כהנים. Kohanim. לא יהיה כהנים. Lo yihyeh kohanim. So if
you read them as one sentence, this idea of kingship is not
for the כהנים, Kohanim, which is specifically pointed. Kingship should extend he
and his children. מאי כתיב בתריה *Mai ketiv batreih*? What does the
next פסוק *pasuk* say right afterwards? לא יהיה לכהנים הלוים *Lo yihyeh
lakohanim haleviyim*. Now the end of it is הכהנים הלויים כל שבט
לוי חלק ונחלה עם ישראל *Hakohanim haleviyim kol shevet Levi chelek venachala
im Yisrael*, right? But the point is juxtaposed to kingship is not
for the כהנים *Kohanim*. לא יהיה לכהנים *Lo yihyeh lakohanim*. So if
you read them as one sentence, this idea of kingship is not
for the כהנים *Kohanim*, which is specifically pointed I would say about
the danger of combining religious leadership with political leadership. אמר רבי יוחנן
*Amar Rabbi Yochanan*, הוא יוחנן הוא יהואחז Yehoachaz *Hu Yochanan hu Yehoachaz*,
the same person in the verse that's יוחנן *Yochanan* is the פסוק
*pasuk* that is יהואחז *Yehoachaz*, because there's a problem here about the
פסוקים *pesukim* because one פסוק *pasuk* says, here I gotta go remind
myself, in דברי הימים *Divrei Hayamim* it says the sons of יאשיהו
*Yoshiyahu* הבכור יוחנן *habechor Yochanan*, and in מלכים *Melachim* it says that
his son was יהואחז *Yehoachaz*. So he says it's exactly it's he's
the same person. והכתיב הבכור יוחנן *Veha ketiv habechor Yochanan*. So it
says the בכור *bechor* is יוחנן *Yochanan* and יהואחז *Yehoachaz* was not
the בכור *bechor*. So it says okay, בכור למלכותו *bechor lemalchuto*. It
means that he was the first one to be the king. That's
what we referred before to, right? יהואחז *Yehoachaz* מפני *mipnei* יהואחז *Yehoachaz*
had the competition with who was it?
Was יהויקים *Yehoyakim*. Okay, so yes, so he was
so
יוחנן/יהואחז *Yochanan/Yehoachaz* was the first to get the מלכות *malchus*, but he
was not the firstborn. And that's why they needed that's why it
says that יהויקים *Yehoyakim* was two years older and he needed to
do the anointing in order to make him the king first. אמר
רבי יוחנן *Amar Rabbi Yochanan*, הוא שלום הוא צדקיהו *hu Shalom hu
Tzidkiyahu*. The same again if you look at the list of the
names of the sons of יאשיהו *Yoshiyahu*, there's also this question of
who is צדקיהו *Tzidkiyahu*, one place says צדקיהו *Tzidkiyahu*, one place says
שלום *Shalom*. Says it's the same person. והכתיב השלישי צדקיהו והרביעי שלום
*Veha ketiv hashlishi Tzidkiyahu vehareviei Shalom*. One minute but one פסוק *pasuk*
says the third son was צדקיהו *Tzidkiyahu* and the fourth one שלום
*Shalom*, so obviously it's not the same person. No, ג' לתולדות *gimel
letoldot*, he was the third in the line of birth, ד' למלכות
*dalet lemalchut*, but the fourth who got the kingship of the sons
of יאשיהו *Yoshiyahu*. So what was the name צדקיהו *Tzidkiyahu*? צדקיהו שצידק
עליו מידת הדין *Tzidkiyahu shetzidak alav midat hadin*, that he justified himself
the divine justice. Now what does that mean? שצידק עליו *Shetzidak alav*.
So does it mean on himself? So you could say it means
that when he went into exile, I think the simple sense of
it means that when he was taken into exile by נבוכדנצר *Nevuchadnezzar*,
he basically said he basically acknowledged that it was just and that
God had acted properly. Not like it's based on any פסוק *pasuk*
that says that, but he accepted the judgment of God. Some of
the מפרשים *mefarshim* want to say based on a בבלי Bavli *Bavli*
that say that the reason that נבוכדנצר *Nevuchadnezzar* calls him צדקיהו *Tzidkiyahu*
was he basically said to him, God will take exact punishment from
you כה יפרעך *ka-yifra'acha* if you rebel against me. So someone writes
that basically נבוכדנצר *Nevuchadnezzar* gave him that name to say you'd better
keep your faith in me and not rebel against me, and then
of course he rebelled against him. So so why they want to
say that צידק עליו את מידת הדין *tzidak alav et midat hadin*
means that נבוכדנצר *Nevuchadnezzar* put just that God would take justice exact
justice against צדקיהו *Tzidkiyahu* if he would rebel. I don't think that's
פשט *pshat* here. I think פשט *pshat* here means that צדקיהו *Tzidkiyahu*
accepted the justice of God at the time of exile.
Whose eyes were put out, was it צדקיהו *Tzidkiyahu*?
Yeah, it was צדקיהו *Tzidkiyahu*.
That was צדקיהו *Tzidkiyahu* whose eyes were put out. Yeah.
So I think it means that he accepted the justice of what
God did. Yeah. שלום *Shalom*, so הגמרא *hagemara* says now what's the
name of שלום *Shalom*? שבימיו שלמה מלכות בית דוד *Shebeyamav shalma malchut
beit David*. Of course שלום *Shalom* is a pretty ironic name. So
it reads it as the sense of completion. In his days the
kingship of דוד *David* came to an end. לא שלום הוה שמו
*Lo Shalom hava shemo*. Now we're just something ריש לקיש *Resh Lakish*
says. You know what, שלום *Shalom* was not his original name ולא
צדקיהו הוה שמו *velo Tzidkiyahu hava shemo*. אלא מתניה *Elah Mattanya*. His
name was מתניה *Mattanya*. How you know? Because it's a פסוק *pasuk*!
הא דכתיב di-chtiv וימלוך מלך בבל את מתניה דודו תחתיו ויסב את
שמו צדקיהו *Ha dechetiv vayimloch melech Bavel et Mattanya dodo tachtav vayasev
et shemo Tzidkiyahu*. So there you go it's a פסוק *pasuk*. It
says that he made מתניה *Mattanya* the king and he switched his
name to be צדקיהו *Tzidkiyahu*. Okay, so there you have it. I
don't really know what you do with I have no idea which
is why maybe they take out the ריש לקיש *Resh Lakish* שמעתא
*shamata* and make it that everybody is agreeing to that.
Yes, the rabbis of the ירושלמי Yerushalmi *Yerushalmi* learned נ"ך *Nach*.
Yes, of the בבלי Bavli *Bavli* too. All right. אמר רבי יוחנן
*Amar Rabbi Yochanan*, now that was a whole little digression about the
שמן המשחה *shemen hamishcha* which was hidden with the ארון aron. *aron*.
But now we're back to the ארון aron *aron*. אמר רבי יוחנן
*Amar Rabbi Yochanan*, and we're going to talk about what what was
stored in the ארון aron. *aron*. Before we had a discussion of
where the שיבי לוחות luchot, *shivei luchot* in a different ארון aron?
*aron*, this one we'll assume that they're not שיבי לוחות luchot, *shivei
luchot*, but it will assume that there's a ספר תורה sefer Torah,
*sefer Torah* because what does it say at the end of דברים
Devarim? *Devarim*, right? It says משה *Moshe* takes the ספר תורה sefer
Torah, *sefer Torah* and says הלוך תשימון אותו מצד mi-tzad ארון aron.
ברית השם *Halo'ach tasimun oto mitzad aron brit Hashem*. So what does
מצד *mitzad* mean? Does it mean inside the ארון aron *aron* on
a side? Does it mean outside the ארון aron *aron* at the
side? So let's take a look. And we're going to discuss the
dimensions of the ארון *aron*. Who the way by the way remembers
what are the dimensions of the ארון *aron*?
אמתים וחצי ארכו *Amataim vachetzi orko*, right?
אמה amah וחצי רחבו *ama vachetzi rochbo*,
right?
Two and a half אמה amah, *ama*, okay we'll discuss how much
an אמה amah *ama* is, by one and a half אמה amah
*ama* רחבו *rochbo*. We don't have to worry about the height now,
we're just going to deal with the width, okay, with the area.
Okay, so that's the ארון *aron*. Now let's take a
look.
Okay, where are we? אמר רבי יוחנן *Amar Rabbi Yochanan*, באמה של
ששה טפחים tefachim היה ארון עשוי *Be'ama shel shisha tefachim haya aron
asui*. It was made with an אמה amah *ama* measure of six
טפחים tefachim, *tefachim* which is a normal אמה amah *ama*. You might
remember that there's a debate in in the בית המקדש *Beit Hamikdash*
was the אמה amah *ama* five טפחים tefachim. *tefachim* or six טפחים
tefachim *tefachim*. מאן תנא Man tana? באמה של ששה טפחים tefachim. *Man
tanna be'ama shel shisha tefachim* So that's רבי מאיר's Rabbi Meir position,
he says, that's רבי מאיר's Rabbi Meir. position, it's a משנה, רבי
מאיר אומר כל האמות היו בינוניות, Rabbi Meir omer kol ha'amot hayu
beinoniyot, all of the אמות amot they used in the בית המקדש
were average six טפחים tefachim ones. רבי יהודה אומר אמות הבנין ששה,
Rabbi Yehuda omer amot habinyan shisha, no, when they used when they
measured the אמה amah for the actual structure itself, it was a
six טפח tefach אמה, ama? ושל כלים חמשה, v'shel kelim chamisha, but
אמות amot that are referred to in terms of the vessels, חמשה,
chamisha, were five. So now we're going to figure it all out
according to רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir, על דעתיה דרבי מאיר, Al daiteh
d'Rabbi Meir, according to רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir. דאמר באמה של ו'
טפחים היה הארון עשוי, du amar ba'amah shel vav tefachim haya ha'aron
asoy,
it was made with a six טפח tefach אמה ama. because it
was that was a כלי, so ארכו של ארון ט"ו טפחים. orko
shel aron tet-vav tefachim.
So the width was fifteen. דכתיב אמתים וחצי ארכו, d'ksiv amatayim vachatzi
orko, so two and a half times six is fifteen. In case
you can't do the math, the בבלי will do the בבלי often
does not do the math for you, the ירושלמי here does. אמתא
שיתא, Amta shisa, one אמה ama. is six טפחים, tefachim, אמתא שיתא
amta shisa the next one is six, ופלגות אמתא תלתא u'palgut amta
tlata the half אמה ama is three. So that's fifteen טפחים. tefachim
וארבע לוחות היו בו. V'arba luchot hayu vo. I'm sorry, I said
before not the שבורות, shvurot, I made a mistake. It does have
the שבורות, shvurot, and there were four of לוחות, luchot the two
שלמים shleimim and two
שבורות shvurot היו בו, hayu vo, שנים שלמים ושנים שבורים. shnayim shleimim
u'shnayim shvurot. The two שלם shalem and the two שבור, shavur, so
not like the idea that the שבור shavur was in a different
ארון, here the שבור shavur was in this ארון, דכתיב אשר שברת
ושמתם בארון, d'ksiv asher shibarta v'samtam ba'aron, you know,
so the that you have broken and you shall place them in
the ארון, so it says as I understand that the לוחות, luchot
even the לוחות luchot, that you broke, was like obviously the פסוק
says you'll make new לוחות luchot just to replace the ones that
you broke and put them, the new ones, in the ארון, but
the way this is reading it is אשר שברת בארון, asher shibarta
ba'aron, even the ones you broke are in the ארון. לוחות ושברי
לוחות מונחים בארון, Luchot v'shivrei luchot munachin ba'aron, as the גמרא says
elsewhere. So that was all in the ארון.
Now, did he say it
went in with them into the מלחמה? milchama? No, no, it denies
that there was a separate ארון that went out to the מלחמה.
milchama. This is that side of debate. Now, הלוחות היו כל אחד
ואחד ארכו ששה ורחבו ששה. Haluchot hayu kol echad v'echad orko shisha
v'rochbo shisha. I have no idea why how this knows it, but
it assumes it takes as granted that they were square לוחות, luchot,
so go tell Cecil B. DeMille this, they were not rectangular, they
certainly didn't have a nice curve and arch at the top, they
were square לוחות luchot, and they were six טפחים tefachim by six
טפחים. tefachim ותן ארכן של לוחות לארכן של ארון. V'tein orkan shel
luchot l'orkan shel aron. Okay, נשתייר שם שלשה טפחים. nishtayer sham shlosha
tefachim. So what would you do? So this was fifteen and this
was nine, okay, so if you had six by six, right, so
that's six here and that's six here, and they assume that they
were stacked, I think, or they assume maybe these were the two
and then the שברי לוחות shivrei luchot, were on top of it,
but I'm assuming that they're assuming that they were stacked. So these
were the two לוחות, luchot, and these presumably although they were broken,
but they took up the same amount of space, were the שברי
לוחות, Luchot okay? So you have six and six, twelve, you have
three left here, and you have three left here of unused space.
Okay, is that clear? Okay. Okay, ותן ארכן של לוחות לארכן של
ארון
נשתייר שם שלשה טפחים.
v'tein orkan shel luchot
l'orkan shel aron nishtayer sham shlosha tefachim. תן מהם חצי טפח לכל
כותל. Tein mehem chatzi tefach l'kol kotel. So now each wall takes
up a half of a טפח. tefach. נשתייר שני טפחים וספר תורה.
Nishtayer shnei tefachim v'sefer Torah. So there's two טפחים tefachim left, we're
talking now in the length, for the ספר תורה, sefer Torah, which
was in the ארון. רחבו של ארון, Rochbo shel aron, okay, so
in these remaining three טפחים, tefachim the three is not three, it's
really two because the width here of the wall is a half
and a half, so it's two, so it's in this two you
put also a ספר תורה, sefer Torah which we're also going to
say was six טפחים tefachim of was six טפחים tefachim long, but
two טפחים tefachim? wide, okay? And this would be your ספר תורה,
sefer Torah. okay? So that was there right alongside, which was narrow.
It's really not so wide. What?
A six טפח tefach ספר תורה sefer Torah is not so crazy,
right? I mean, you know, okay, it's small, but it's not like
one of those ספרי תורה sifrei Torah that they make. Okay, right.
So that's where they had the ספר תורה. sefer Torah, Okay, תן,
now,
רחבו של ארון ששה טפחים, tefachim, דכתיב אמה וחצי רחבו, d'ksiv amah
vachatzi rochbo,
an אמה amah and a half was its width. אמתא שיתא ופלגות
אמתא תלתא, Amta shisa u'palgut amta tlata, an אמה is six, a
half אמה is three. וארבע לוחות היו בו, V'arba luchot hayu vo,
and there were the four לוחות, Luchot, like we said, this is
just going to be so repetitious here. שנים שלמים ושנים שבורים shnayim
shleimim u'shnayim shvurot דכתיב אשר שברת ושמתם בארון d'ksiv asher shibarta v'samtam
ba'aron והלוחות היו כל אחד ואחד ארכן ששה ורחבן ששה טפחים, v'haluchot
hayu kol echad v'echad orkan shisha v'rochban shisha tefachim,
like it said the whole thing but it's repeating it again, they
were six by six. Now it's repeating it when it's talking about
the width exactly what it said by the length. תן רחבן של
לוחות לרחבן של ארון נשתייר שם שלשה טפחים. Tein rochban shel luchot
l'rochban shel aron nishtayer sham shlosha tefachim. Now width-wise we have three
טפחים tefachim left. חצי טפח מכאן לכותל זה וחצי טפח מכאן לכותל
זה. Chatzi tefach mikan l'kotel zeh v'chatzi tefach mikan l'kotel zeh. Each
wall took up a half טפח. tefach. וטפחיים לשירוש מקום, V'tefachyim l'shirush
makom,
and two טפחים tefachim are left for like, you know, a little
breathing space, access space, שהספר תורה מונח, she'ha'sefer Torah munach, because that's
where the ספר תורה Sefer Torah? was. So actually you have two
טפחים tefachim. here that is un nothing is in it. Now maybe
you actually did it more logically and you put a טפח tefach
on each side, right, so it's not so it's a little bit
so you can get it out, you can get access and you
get it out. Now presumably they didn't want to get out the
לוחות, Luchot. but they would sometimes want to take out the ספר
תורה, Sefer Torah okay? So this was totally tight, six, six, and
two. where the sort of- was the width, but there was a
טפח tefach on each side to allow some type of access, wiggle
space.
They never showed that they read on- like on יום כיפור?
Yom Kippur? Presumably not. That, anyway, that comes up later in the
משנה. It's not clear. Right, okay.
Okay, so the
לוחות luchot were only- no, because
there's four of them, right?
Yeah, but I think it's assumed they were stacked. But that's actually
a good question. One גירסא girsa had שלוש shalosh and put in
parentheses for שישה. shisha. So if you had the גירסא girsa שלושה,
shlosha, then it would have actually been like this. If your גירסא
girsa was שלושה, shlosha, and that actually would be the- that's the
basis of the גירסא girsa שלושה, shlosha, with our גירסא girsa שישה,
shisha, then they're square and they were stacked on top of one
another.
Which would have six אמה?
And with שישה. shisha. If it's three, then it does have them
as a more- what as we imagine them- a more rectangular shape
rather than a square.
But the מדרשי Midrashic tradition has them as a square.
Right. Okay, square six טפחים tefachim. by six טפחים? Right. Okay. טפחים,
right. Okay. So, okay,
that's that. Okay. רבי שמעון בן לקיש אומר באמה בת חמישה טפחים
היה הארון, Rebbe Shimon ben Lakish omer, be'ama bat chamisha tefachim haya
ha'aron, no, it was made with five טפח tefach אמה. באמה בת
חמישה טפחים היה הארון. Be'ama bat chamisha tefachim haya ha'aron. מאן תנא?
באמה בת חמישה טפחים? Be'ama bat chamisha tefachim? רבי יהודה. Rebbe Yehuda.
That's רבי יהודה. Rebbe Yehuda. דתנן התם רבי יהודה
אומר אמת הבניין שישה ושל כל
הכלים חמישה, Detnan hatam, Rebbe Yehuda omer, amat habinyan shisha veshel kol
hakelim chamisha, six טפחים for structure, five טפחים for vessels. והארון כלי
הוא, Veha'aron keli hu, it's a vessel. על דעתיה דרבי יהודה דאמר
באמה של
חמישה טפחים היה אורכו, Al daiteh deRebbe Yehuda de'amar be'ama shel chamisha
tefachim haya orko, since it was a vessel, you used a five
טפח tefach אמה. So now what- how does that translate? היה אורכו
עשוי שנים עשר טפח ומחצה. Haya orko asoi shneim asar tefach umachetza.
So since two and a
half times five gets you twelve and a half. דכתיב אמתים וחצי
אורכו, Dechtiv amatayim vachetzi orko, אמתא חמישה אמתא חמישה, amta chamisha amta
chamisha, each אמה'ס ama's five, that's ten, ופלגא דאמתא תרי ופלגי, ufalgat
amta trei uphalgi, two and a half, so now we have twelve
and a half.
So now we've got to get the לוחות, luchot which are twelve
wide, into a twelve and a half. Doesn't give you too much
space. ארבעה לוחות היו בו, Arba luchot hayu bo, שניים שלמים ושניים
שבורים, shnayim shlemim ushnayim shvurim, דכתיב אשר שברת ושמתם בארון. dechtiv asher
shibarta vesamtam ba'aron. So that tells us the broken ones were there.
והלוחות היו כל אחד ואחד אורכן שישה ורוחבן שישה, Vehaluchot hayu kol
echad ve'echad orchan shisha verochban shisha, or שלושה, shlosha, depending on your
גירסא. girsa. Okay? But they'll take up twelve wide, טפחים. תן אורכן
של לוחות לאורכו של
ארון, Ten orchan shel luchot le'orko shel aron, lie
their length by the length of your ארון, ונשתייר שם חצי טפח.
venishtayer sham chatzi tefach. According to this, instead of sixteen, we have
twelve. By the way, here instead of- now you're going to have
seven and a half. You have six and six for the-
and you have twelve and a half. You have- right, because two
and a half times five. Six and six for the לוחות. luchot.
Either again they're stacked on top of one another or the גירסא
girsa is three and they're side-by-side. But either way, combined they're twelve
and the whole thing is twelve and a half. So what it's
going to say is you have the walls are like paper thin.
The walls are one אצבע. etzba. An אצבע etzba is a quarter
of a טפח, tefach, because you've got four. Okay? So you've got
a quarter here for a wall and a quarter here for a
wall and the whole thing just barely fits. Okay? Is that clear?
When you put the אצבע etzba on a דף of- six, six
and the walls are one אצבע etzba wide and the whole thing
is your exact twelve and a half. Okay? So yeah, so what
are you going to do with the ספר תורה? sefer Torah Okay.
ונשתייר שם חצי אצבע. Venishtayer sham chatzi etzba. אצבע לכותל
מכאן ואצבע לכותל מכאן. Etzba lekothel mikan ve'etzba lekothel mikan. רוחבו של
ארון, Rochbo shel aron, its width, שבעה טפחים ומחצה, shiva tefachim vamachetza,
seven and a half. דכתיב אמה וחצי רוחבו. Dechtiv ama vachetzi rochbo.
So
an אמה and a half. אמתא חמישה ופלגא דאמתא תרי
ופלגי, Amta chamisha uphalga amta trei uphalgi, five and two and a
half. וארבעה לוחות היו בו, Ve'arba luchot hayu bo, שניים שלמים ושניים
שבורים, shnayim shlemim ushnayim shvurim, דכתיב אשר שברת ושמתם בארון. dechtiv asher
shibarta vesamtam ba'aron. והלוחות היו כל אחד ואחד אורכן שישה טפחים, Vehaluchot
hayu kol echad ve'echad orchan shisha tefachim, it was six, ורוחבן שישה,
verochban shisha, and it was six wide, טפחים. תן רוחבן לרוחבן של
ארון. Ten rochban lerochban shel aron.
So now the six goes against the six of a seven and
a half. So what you have, ונשתייר שם טפח ומחצה. venishtayer sham
tefach vamachetza. So now at least you have a little breathing room,
a טפח tefach and a bit. אצבע לכותל מכאן ואצבע לכותל מכאן.
Etzba lekothel mikan ve'etzba lekothel mikan. Again, the walls are uniform size,
so they're an אצבע. etzba. That covers the half. So now you
have left one טפח tefach widthwise. חצי טפח מכאן וחצי טפח מכאן
לשלוט, Chatzi tefach mikan vechatzi tefach mikan lishilut,
a half of a טפח tefach here and a half of a
טפח tefach there for space. So basically you had- this was twelve
and a half, so this was six and six and the walls
made the half. This was seven and a half, this was six,
so the walls here got you a half, so that for- so
now you have a whole טפח tefach left. And that טפח, tefach,
you had a half of a טפח tefach here and a half
of a טפח tefach here for some like
air circulation or something.
What did they put in then? Okay, well that'll all be on
the side. Okay, so according to this, you couldn't get the ספר
תורה sefer Torah in. לשלוט. Lishilut.
Where were we? Okay. Now, כיצד עשה בצלאל
את הארון, Keitzad asa Betzalel et ha'aron, how did he do it?
רבי חנניא אומר שלוש תיבות עשאו, Rebbe Chananya omer, shalosh teivot asao,
he made three separate boxes,
שתיים של זהב ואחת של עץ, shtayim shel zahav ve'achat shel etz,
he made them separately, independently of
a box- two boxes of gold, one of wood. נתן של זהב
בשל עץ Natan shel zahav beshel etz It's a very bizarre way
to plate something. But וצפו ve-tzipu and then he you know and
then he sort of and then he coated it דכתיב di-chtiv וצפיתו
זהב טהור מבית ומחוץ ve-tzapita oto zahav tahor mi-bayit u-mi-chutz מה תלמוד
לומר mah talmud lomar וצפנו? ve-tzipanu? What's the extra verb וצפנו? ve-tzipanu?
כדי להביא
שפתותיו העליונה kedai le-havi siftotav ha-elyonah that after you
after you stack them or not stack them whatever insert them you
know at the top you'll still see that they're separate. So then
you cover the top you know the top flat part of the
top where they're all stacked together you know where they're all inserted
and anyway it holds it together anyway so you cover that with
a plating of gold.
That's which is very strange I don't know why he assumes that.
ריש לקיש אמר he gives a different explanation. No, תיבה אחת עשה.
teivah achat asah. He made one box. He started with wood. וצפו.
ve-tzipu. And then he and then he plated it. He coated it
over with gold. דכתיב De-chtiv וצפיתו זהב טהור מבית ומחוץ ve-tzapita oto
zahav tahor mi-bayit u-mi-chutz מה תלמוד לומר mah talmud lomar וצפנו? ve-tzipanu?
Why do you need according to this the extra verse וצפנו? ve-tzipanu?
אמר רב פנחס Amar Rav Pinchas להביא בין נסר לנסר. le-havi bein
neser le-neser.
He even did it between the planks which I'm not exactly understanding.
I guess it means that even if you made it out of
wood and there was like some... I often you know when you
assume that he made that he made the ארון out of wood
you assume that it means that there was planks that were put
together. I assumed it meant one piece of wood that was carved
out to be the ארון. Anyway he understands that there were somehow
different planks right and maybe it's certainly between when you go from
like the wall to the you know to the base or something
so you made sure I guess that the gold even went into
the crevices there between the planks.
But וצפיתו זהב טהור ve-tzapita oto zahav tahor does it mean it
really was זהב טהור zahav tahor or just wood?
No, you're וצפיתו ve-tzapita the wooden one. It says ועשית ארון עצי
שטים ve-asita aron atzei shitim you make it out of עצי שטים.
atzei shitim. No, but he thinks
it was all one thing.
Did he say that?
Yeah, it was out of wood that was then coated with gold.
That's exactly what the פסוק says.
That means really the plating then.
The plating is זהב טהור, zahav tahor, right. Exactly. Yeah. Okay. בין
נסר לנסר. Bein neser le-neser. Okay. כיצד היו לוחות כתובים? Keitzad hayu
luchot ketuvim?
Now, how were the לוחות luchot. written? רבי חנניה בן גמליאל Rabbi
Chananya ben Gamliel אומר omer חמישה על לוח זה וחמישה על לוח
זה. chamishah al luach zeh ve-chamishah al luach zeh. That makes sense,
five on each לוח. luach. Like we understand you know the way
we always assume. By the way the תורה Torah never says five
on each לוח. luach. But you know the whole idea בין אדם
למקום bein adam la-Makom ובין אדם לחברו. ve-bein adam la-chavero. We always
assume that that's what it is. There's ten, they're divided equally. Yeah.
וחמישה על לוח זה. ve-chamishah al luach zeh. רבנן Rabbanan אמרי, amri,
the rabbis say, דכתיב De-chtiv,
that's what's meant by ויכתבם על שני לוחות אבנים. va-yichtivem al shenei
luchot avanim. They were written on the two לוחות luchot. so somehow
the fact that they're treated sort of all you know equally means
an equal division. חמישה על לוח זה וחמישה על לוח זה. chamishah
al luach zeh ve-chamishah al luach zeh. רבנן Rabbanan אמרי, amri, the
rabbis say, עשרה על לוח זה ועשרה על לוח זה. asarah al
luach zeh ve-asarah al luach zeh. They were repeated. Ten on each
לוח. luach. Each לוח luach had all of the עשרת הדברות. One
in שמות Shemot and one in דברים?
Devarim Oh that's interesting.
I don't think so. Let's keep on reading. Let's keep on reading.
I'll tell you after.
Let's read a little and then we can talk about it. But
I... that's an interesting suggestion that the שמות Shemot and דברים were...
דכתיב De-chtiv, that's what's meant and ויגד לכם את בריתו אשר צוה
אתכם לעשות עשרת הדברים va-yaged lachem et brito asher tzivah etchem la-asot
aseret ha-devarim as he told and ויכתבם על שני לוחות אבנים va-yichtivem
al shenei luchot avanim is the end of the פסוק. So עשרת
הדברים aseret ha-devarim ויכתבם על שני לוחות. va-yichtivem al shenei luchot. So
each of
the עשרת הדברים aseret ha-devarim
were written on each of the two לוחות. luchot. עשרה על לוח
זה ועשרה על לוח זה. asarah al luach zeh ve-asarah al luach
zeh. Now רבי שמעון בן יוחאי Rabbi Shimon ben Yochai אומר omer
עשרים על לוח זה ועשרים על לוח זה. esrim al luach zeh
ve-esrim al luach zeh. This is sort of like you know the
הגדה, Haggadah, right? Oh 50, 50, 250! So now what does it
mean עשרים? esrim? So here what he clearly means is the same
ten were written on each לוח luach front and back. Okay? Not
a different 20? Right. So עשרים על לוח זה ועשרים על לוח
זה. esrim al luach zeh ve-esrim al luach zeh. Because he basically
says ויכתבם va-yichtivem means he wrote two of them and each two
על שני לוחות אבנים. al shenei luchot avanim. על לוח זה. al
luach zeh. רבי סימאי Rabbi Simai אומר ארבעים על לוח זה וארבעים
על לוח זה. arbaim al luach zeh ve-arbaim al luach zeh. On
all four sides of the לוחות. luchot Okay? דכתיב de-chtiv, מזה ומזה
הם כתובים. mi-zeh u-mi-zeh hem ketuvim.
טטרוגא, tetroga, like a tetragon, like a four-sided like a square. It's
a Greek word טטרוגא, tetroga, right? Tetra. So cube. But
so basically so here the... what? You have to see right we
next thing we should be saying is six. But anyway so here
just this is why I don't think it means different versions because
when it's talking here about 20 and 40 obviously it's talking about
the same thing on all sides. I've heard other midrashim. No, it
could be but I'm just saying I don't think that's the sense
here. And I think the sense here is like you know no
matter where you it's sort of like no matter which way you
look at it it's always giving it's like there's always the same
message you know? It's not like you know the תורה Torah only
speaks to you from something of that sense or like you know
that looking at it from front, backwards, up and down you always
see the same truth. Okay.
In ancient times when you'd have a treaty you would have two
stones, one for each party of the treaty. Ah okay so that
explains at least the 20 idea, that's a nice thought. What did
he say? He said in ancient times when you'd have a treaty
each party would get a stone like nowadays each party takes home
a copy of the contract so you have the same thing on
each stone. But then it gets to 20 and 40 and so
on. Okay. חנניה בן אחי רבי יהושע Chananya ben achi Rabbi Yehoshua
אומר בין כל דיבור ודיבור. bein kol dibur ve-dibur. Now here's a
fascinating idea between... in each of the עשרת הדיברות, Aseret HaDibrot, דקדוקיה
ואותיותיה של תורה dikdukeiha v'otioteiha shel Torah
was written all of the explications of that דיבור. dibbur So all
of the like the תורה שבעל פה Torah she-be'al peh about that
דיבור was written in the spare, in the white space between the
דיבורים. dibburim. I don't know if it was literally written or what
he means. דכתיב and he quotes the פסוק from שיר השירים, Shir
HaShirim, ממולאים בתרשיש memula'im ba-tarshish
filled with תרשיש, Tarshish, which is some type of a precious stone,
כימא רבא kiyama rabba like the big ocean, which is, he understood
as, תרשיש Tarshish is the name of the big ocean. Now where
does he get that idea? So רבא רב שמעון בן לקיש, Rabba
Rav Shimon ben Lakish, כד הוה מטי בהדין קרא, kad hava mati
be-hadain kra, when they would come to this פסוק, הוה אמר, hava
amar, יפה למדני yafe limadani חנניה בן אחי רבי יהושע. Chananya ben
achi Rabbi Yehoshua. He taught me well about what this פסוק means.
מה הים הזה ma ha-yam ha-zeh בין גל גדול לגל גדול bein
gal gadol le-gal gadol גלים קטנים, galim ktanim,
the same way in a big ocean between every large wave there
are a lot of those like small little waves and ripples that
occur between the large waves, כך בין כל דיבור ודיבור, kach bein
kol dibbur ve-dibbur, between every one of the דיברות, dibrot, דקדוקיה ואותיותיה
של תורה dikdukeiha ve-otioteiha shel Torah
were all of the little explications and you know all the little
waves. Now again does it literally mean that they were written or
is this more meant like symbolically and metaphorically like in that white
space between the דיברות dibrot all of the implications somehow were implicit?
A source for the image or metaphor of the ים של תלמוד?
yam shel Talmud?
I was wondering about that.
That's not easy to find.
I was wondering about that. Let's just finish this, okay. אמר רב
תנחומא, Amar Rav Tanchuma, איתקשיה קומי רבי פנחס, itkashya kumi Rabbi Pinchas,
I asked a question before Rabbi פנחס. Pinchas. אשכח רבי יהודה ולא
אשכח רבי מאיר. Ashkach Rabbi Yehuda ve-lo ashkach Rabbi Meir. So a
proof that shows like רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that it was חמשה
טפחים chamisha tefachim per אמה not like רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir מאי
טעמא דרבי יהודה? Mai ta'ama de-Rabbi Yehuda? What's the reason of רבי
יהודה? Rabbi Yehuda? דכתיב, לקוח את ספר התורה הזה ושמתם אותו מצד
ארון ברית ה'. Lakoach et sefer ha-Torah ha-zeh ve-samtem oto mi-tzad aron
berit Hashem.
So that takes it and put it by the side of the
ארון, which meant that it was outside of the ארון. So על
דעתיה דרבי יהודה, al da'atei de-Rabbi Yehuda, דו אמר, du amar, היכן
היה ספר תורה נתון? heichan haya sefer Torah natun?
So according to רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, where was the ספר תורה
sefer Torah, placed? כמין גלוסקמיא k'min gluskamya עשויה לו מבחוץ, asuyah lo
mi-bachutz,
they had some type of a box on the outside of the
ארון attached on the outside. וספר תורה נתון בתוכה ve-sefer Torah natun
betochah and the ספר תורה sefer Torah would be put inside because
as we just heard according to him there's no room for it
inside the ארון. So מצד means on the outside presumably. מאי טעמא
דרבי מאיר? Mai ta'ama de-Rabbi Meir? Now what's the reason of רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir, that says it was in the ארון? דכתיב, ונתת
את הכפורת על הארון מלמעלה, ve-natata et ha-kaporet al ha-aron milma'ala, you
put the כפורת kaporet on the ארון. ואל הארון תתן את העדות
אשר אתן אליך. ve-el ha-aron titein et ha-edut asher etein eilecha. So
and to the ארון you will put the עדות edut which I
will give you.
So now what does that mean? That the ארון was already covered.
You said you put the כפורת. kaporet. So that seems to prove
like רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. It seems to be that
he understands the עדות edut here meaning the ספר תורה, not the
לוחות. I would say the simple sense of the פסוק it's the
לוחות. So it says according to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda it makes
sense. You cover it and you put the לוחות on the like
little box attached to the side. But according to, according to רבי
מאיר, what do you do? It's already covered. So it says על
דעתיה דרבי מאיר, al da'atei de-Rabbi Meir, דו אמר, du amar, אין
מוקדם ומאוחר בתורה. ein mukdam u-me'uchar ba-Torah. Now it's not in order,
meaning cover it, but before you cover it put the ספר תורה
inside. So although it says put the עדות edut after, it really
obviously would be put before you would cover it. ואל הארון תתן
את העדות אשר אתן אליך, ve-el ha-aron titein et ha-edut asher etein
eilecha, אחר כך ונתת את הכפורת על הארון מלמעלה. achar kach ve-natata
et ha-kaporet al ha-aron milma'ala. Okay. Last point. אמר רבי פנחס בשם
רבי שמעון בן לקיש, Amar Rabbi Pinchas beshem Rabbi Shimon ben Lakish,
התורה שנתן לו הקדוש ברוך הוא למשה, ha-Torah she-natan lo ha-Kadosh Baruch
Hu le-Moshe, נתנה לו אש לבנה חרוטה באש שחורה. netanah lo esh
levana charuta be-esh shechora.
White fire written on, now there's two readings of this. Is it
white fire written on black fire? Are the letters white? Or is
it white fire written with black fire and the the fire the
ink as it were is the black fire, which makes sense, right?
Like black ink on a white surface. היא אש מבללה באש hi
esh mevuiela be-esh fire intertwined with fire. אש חצובה מאש esh chatzuva
me-esh fire hewn out of fire, ונתונה מאש u-netunah me-esh and given
out of fire דכתיב, מימינו אש דת למו, mi-ymino esh dat lamo,
it was a fiery thing.
So again all of this discussion about the physicality of it, it
ends by obviously emphasizing you know its divine nature and the impossibility
of embodying it in any type of a physical reality. Okay and
we're going...